All right, we pick up today on
דף יב Daf Yud Bet and we started a new פרק perek
and the basic point of this פרק perek is, well later we'll
discuss it about how one brings a חטאת chatas and how many
חטאות chatasos one can bring. So and the focus actually is quite
interesting because it's based on the fact that the תורה Torah says
when it speaks about bringing a חטאת, chatas, או הודע אליו חטאתו,
o hoda alav chatato, that his sin becomes known to him. So
saying that his sin becomes known to him, on the one hand
it says he's not, it doesn't say sort of he becomes aware
himself, but it also says that it sounds like at the end
he acknowledges it. And therefore that leads to the important question about
how much does he himself have to be aware that he has
sinned or how much can other people inform him. So the משנה
Mishna yesterday had spoken about the fact, thank you so much, if
people tell him that he has sinned, it's one witness
or anything short of two witnesses, then the only time he would
have to bring the חטאת chatas is if he is silent, which
implicitly is interpreted to mean that he, that he you know admits
to and acknowledges it. So he's really not bringing it on the
basis of the other person's testimony, he's bringing his חטאת chatas on
the on the implicit you know on his own implicit acknowledgment. תוספות
Tosafos even goes so far to say that if a witness says
you sinned and he says I don't know, meaning all right maybe
you're right, I personally don't know, I'm not saying not, that he
would not bring, that it requires him to actually either explicitly or
implicitly acknowledge that he has sinned and even and so silence works
but I don't know doesn't work. Now we turn to a fascinating
debate of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and חכמים Chachamim of what if
it's two witnesses? Because two witnesses provides us for normal purposes incontrovertible
proof that objectively it has happened, two witnesses says he's done it,
and the question still remains is he if he if he contradicts
them says no you say I did it but I didn't do
it, maybe he doesn't bring the חטאת chatas even if we know
that he has sinned, maybe it still requires his own acceptance and
admission of that even if objectively we know it's happened. So that's
the question of two witnesses say he's done it and he contradicts,
does he bring the חטאת chatas or not. So again we pick
up at the top of דף יב עמוד א, Daf Yud Bet
Amud Aleph, second line from the top. אמר רבי מאיר קל וחומר,
Amar Rabbi Meir kal vachomer, so רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says it's
a קל וחומר kal vachomer if witnesses can make him bring to
put him to death then they can certainly make him bring a
קרבן. korban. And the רבנן Rabbanan say no, since he could have
said,
let me just take a look at the line in the משנה,
Mishna, right, אם רצה לומר מזיד הייתי, im ratza lomar meizid hayiti,
if he could have said he was intentional, so therefore even if
the witnesses say he does it, it's no proof that he actually
brings a חטאת, chatas, maybe he was doing it intentionally. Let's take
a look at what this line means. So the גמרא Gemara right
from the beginning says, איבעיא להו, ibayu lehu, we ask, מאי טעמא
דרבנן, mai taama de-rabbanan, what's the reason of the רבנן Rabbanan that
say that he does not have to bring in this case? Is
it because משום דאדם נאמן על עצמו יותר ממאה איש, mishum de-adam
ne'eman al atzmo yoter mi-me'ah ish, a person is believed on himself
more than a hundred people, או דילמא משום דאמרינן מיגו, o dilma
mishum de-amrinan migo, or because we say מיגו, migo, which means since.
What does since mean? דאי בעי אמר מזיד הייתי, de-i ba'ei amar
meizid hayiti, like the language of the משנה Mishna says, since anyway
he could get out of it by claiming I was intentional, פטור,
patur, and then he would have been exempt from a קרבן, korban,
כי אמר נמי לא אכלתי, ki amar nami lo achalti, even if
he says he did not eat, מהימן ופטור, meheman u-fatur, so then
he's also believed because he could have gotten out of it another
way. Now both of these statements are both of these possibilities are
a little bit unusual. Normally when we say a person is believed
on himself, right we say הודאת בעל דין כמאה עדים דמי. hoda'as
ba'al din ke-me'ah edim dami. If I admit that I owe you
a hundred dollars or whatever I admit I owe you, it's like
a hundred witnesses because I am obligating myself, so I am believed
to obligate myself. That's when we say a person is believed about
himself. Here it's the opposite, here I'm saying I didn't do it,
I didn't do it, so therefore why should I be believed about
myself? So רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafos immediately qualify it by saying
no, here you're believed about yourself because we don't think you would
lie when it comes to an issue about you know you getting
atonement from God. So because like people wouldn't lie about that, of
course you'd want to be atoned for. So in this special circumstance
we're going to believe that ultimately you would only tell the truth
more than what you know. Now why
the witnesses know? No, you say I don't, no you say I
didn't, you don't say I don't know.
Okay, what if they're false witnesses?
They could be false witnesses, right. Now even that explanation that here
it's special because you would not lie about your own atonement is
a little strange because normally we would say that witnesses are stronger
than any supposition of how you know that we would make about
would you normally lie or not lie in these circumstances. So I
think and I laid this out yesterday that there's other reasons to
say here according to the חכמים Chachamim we believe you more than
the witnesses. One and two I'll say the two of them. One
is
is that it's not really an issue of believing you more. We
might believe the witnesses. But as we learned from the previous פסוק
pasuk או הודע אליו o hoda alav and we're going to quote
another פסוק pasuk והתודה ve-hisvada that it speaks about your own acceptance.
said admission, like וידוי, Viduy, right? הודאת החטא, Hodat hachet, you know,
accepting the case, admitting that you sinned. Even if we know you
sinned, you don't bring a חטאת Chatas until you yourself personally own
up to it. Owning up to it is part of the process
of bringing a חטאת. Chatas. Okay, so then it's not really about
believing you and not believing them. We believe them, but you're still
not going to bring the חטאת Chatas until you own up to
it. That's not like what the גמרא Gemara counts in either of
these options, right? It says either because you're believed or because you
could have said something else. But one possibility certainly is that even
if we believe the witnesses, although that's not what the גמרא Gemara
is saying here, even if we believe the witnesses, part of bringing
a חטאת Chatas is owning up to your sin. The other possibility
is, and this maybe fits more with the language of you're believed
about yourself, and this is a point I said the other day,
is that the גמרא Gemara in ערכין Erchin says that we even
if we know you have to bring a חטאת, Chatas, בית דין
Beis Din is not going to compel you to do so. We're
not going to seize your property. It's right, חייבי חטאות אין ממשכנין
אותם. Chayavei chatas ein memashkenin osam. We learned it in ערכין. Erchin.
Why? Because it's not our business. You know, if you've sinned, like
and it's something that's punishable by the court or if it's a
civil liability, then we're going to get involved in it. But this
is not about punishing you. This is about you doing תשובה Teshuvah
and you getting
sort of, you know, forgiven by God. That's between you and God.
That's not our business. So if that's why we're not going to
compel you to bring a חטאת, Chatas, even if we know you're
obligated, it could also be why when it comes to who do
we believe, it's not our business. Witnesses is an idea for the
court. If it's something that's fundamentally our business, we listen to the
witnesses, we believe them. This is fundamentally about you and God. Fundamentally
about you and God, who cares about the witnesses? It's about what
you say. Okay, so that is I think a radical but possible,
radical only in the sense that it's making a very strong statement,
way to read the first line that you're believed about yourself more
than witnesses. Not just because obviously you're telling the truth, but because
at the end of the day, it's not between about us and
the courts and witnesses, it's about you and God. One second. The
other approach is that we believe you because you could have said
I did it intentionally. Now, and you would have gotten off anyway.
Now, that idea of מיגו, Migo, believe me because when I say
this, because I could have said something else. There's a big problem.
You'd be a רשע. Rasha.
Well, right. There's two problems. Number one is you would never have
wanted to say you did it intentionally, right? That makes you look
terrible. It makes you look like you're a willful sinner. So what
do you mean I could have said I did it intentionally? Number
one. Number two is we normally don't say that because, you know,
since I could have said A, believe me when I said B.
We don't say that to beat out witnesses. Witnesses at the end
of the day are strong, are the strongest proof. מיגו במקום עדים
לא אמרינן.
Migo bemakom
eidim lo amrinan.
So therefore, why just because you could have said something else should
we believe you now to win out against witnesses? So תוספות Tosafos
says you're right and we really don't mean a classic מיגו. Migo.
What we really mean, as the גמרא Gemara is going to say
in a minute, is is that since there were other ways that
you could get out of it, we would be more inclined to
reinterpret what you said here. And when you said I didn't do
it, what you really meant to say was, you know, I didn't
do it in a way that I would have to bring a
קרבן. Korban. I didn't do, you meaning, meaning I didn't do it
unintentionally, I did it intentionally. Or I did, right, but meaning, no,
but not like we believe you that you didn't do it. What
it really means is we're going to reinterpret your statement in a
way to get you out of the consequence of what the witness
said. So when you said you didn't do it, we'll interpret it
to say I didn't do it unintentionally, I did it intentionally. So
it's a, it's another phrase called in the גמרא Gemara not called
מיגו, Migo, but called מפרשינן דיבוריה. Mefarshinan diburei. We will try to
reinterpret your statement for your benefit. So it's in your benefit here,
i.e., not to bring a קרבן. Korban.
Well, no, but isn't it a benefit to bring a קרבן? Korban?
Because let's say you did it מזיד.
Meizid. No, if you did it מזיד Meizid without התראה, Hasra'ah, the
witnesses aren't saying that they warned you, so you're not going to
get a punishment either. So the way you get out of anything
is I did it מזיד Meizid without any warning. Now again, the
question is, okay, but why are we invested in reinterpreting your statement
to get you out of it? Right? Why should we make you
say something like that in order to work around the witnesses? And
again, I think you have to say what's compelling us is the
idea that bringing a קרבן Korban at the end of the day
is more of an issue between you and God than it is
an issue of the court and the witnesses. So that even if,
so maybe if there's blatant evidence we can't ignore it, okay, but
we will try as much as we can to sort of get
this, you know, work around the witnesses. So that would be the
second approach. So the one approach is we just completely believe you
against the witnesses. You're believed more than the witnesses. And the other
is because we can reframe the statement. And now we're going to
look, what difference does it make which approach you say? Yes.
Can a known sinner even be believed at all?
Yeah, well, I mean, there's, yes, there's a question about how, what
type of a sin do you have to do to have a
status of being a פסול לעדות? Pasul le'eidus? But that's also questions
about פסול לעדות Pasul le'eidus as opposed to have נאמנות, Ne'emanus, and
that's a whole סוגיא Sugya about חשוד, Chashud, that if somebody is,
you know, חשוד Chashud on one, is he חשוד Chashud over another?
But anyway, the point here is is that, yeah, I hear your
point. If you're saying you sinned, why don't we say that that
undermines
your... on this, חשוד *chashud* on the other thing, but would we
say that if you're only על פי עצמו *al pi atzmo*? Yeah,
again, probably not. Probably it would get back to the principle that
Michael said of אין אדם משים עצמו רשע *ein adam mesim atzmo
rasha*. So we believe you enough that you did it במזיד bemazid
*bemezid* so you don't have to bring a קרבן korban? *korban*, but
not enough that it actually lead to פסול *pasul*-ing you. Although it's
interesting because it is a little
circular. We'd get into another principle which is לא מטרצינן דיבוריה *lo
metartzinnan diburei* but פלגינן דיבורא *palginan dibura*. We only believe you for
half that's relevant and not the half that we don't want to
believe you for. So yeah, Michael.
We have one other question. The other, you know, I'm just thinking
about the structure of the משנה Mishnah *mishna*. It's either
two say this and then he doesn't. Usually say רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir *Rabbi Meir* says this, וחכמים *vachachamim* say that. וחכמים *vachachamim* say
that. Then רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* says to them and
you know, they sort of left out, it's sort of almost implied.
I mean, hasn't he picked up that... Yeah, I know.
But yeah, that's true. That might be because it is a, because
the obvious question here is that the witness doesn't have a place
altogether. So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir. *Rabbi Meir* has to start with
that argument. Okay, let's take a look now how the גמרא Gemara.
*gemara* develops this, okay?
So it says like this. Okay, so again we have two possibilities.
One is you're just סתם *stam* believed, which as I've suggested just
means that it's not about witnesses, it's about you, about you and
God. And the other is that we'll believe you to the degree
that we can reinterpret your words so that they get you out
of it. So now the גמרא Gemara *gemara* says what's the נפקא
מינה *nafka mina*? So the גמרא Gemara *gemara* says, now again, you're
about halfway down on the דף *daf*, ומאי נפקא מינה *umai nafka
mina*, what difference does it make which approach we take? למפשט מיניה
לטומאה *limfashat minei letuma*, to whether we can apply it for a
case of טומאה tumah. *tuma*. What's the case? דאי אמרת טעמייהו דרבנן
משום דאדם נאמן על עצמו יותר ממאה איש ne'eman al atzmo yoter
mi-me'ah ish. *de'i amrat ta'ameihu derabbanan mishum de'adam ne'eman al atzmo yoter
mimaya ish*, if it's because you're just believed about yourself more than
the witnesses, לא שנא טומאה tumah, חדשה ולא שנא טומאה tumah. ישנה
*lo shena tuma chadasha velo shena tuma yeshana*, it doesn't matter new
or old טומאה tumah, *tuma*. What's the case? The case is witnesses
say to you, you became טמא tamei *tamei*, and then you ate
a קרבן korban. *korban* or went into the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash,
*Beis HaMikdash*. And you say, no, I didn't become טמא tamei *tamei*.
Now, when you say I didn't become טמא tamei, *tamei*, it's not
a question of that you can מטרצינן דיבוריה *metartzinnan diburei* reinterpret it
to mean oh I didn't do it בשוגג beshogeg. *beshogeg*, I did
it במזיד bemazid *bemezid*. The issue is not how you became טמא
tamei, *tamei*, the issue is the sin is eating the קרבן korban.
*korban* afterwards or going to the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash, *Beis HaMikdash*.
So remember, how do you get around what the witnesses say? You
say yeah, I did it, but I did it in a way
that I don't have to bring a קרבן korban. *korban*. I did
it במזיד b'meizid, *bemezid*, not בשוגג beshogeg. *beshogeg*. That's only if you're
talking about the action of the sin. But here, if what you're
denying is having become טמא tamei, *tamei*, which preceded the sin, right,
first you became טמא tamei. *tamei* then you ate the קרבן korban.
*korban*, and they said you became טמא tamei. *tamei* and I said
I didn't become טמא tamei *tamei*. How are we going to get
you out of that? Right? בשוגג b'shogeg, *beshogeg* במזיד b'meizid. *bemezid* doesn't
matter. So it's going to matter though, here's the difference. I didn't
become טמא tamei, *tamei* can be reinterpreted to not contradict the witnesses
and to get you out of it by saying I didn't remain
טמא tamei, *tamei*. You say I became טמא tamei, *tamei*, I say
I didn't, which means that I didn't, means I didn't remain טמא
tamei, *tamei*, I went to the מקוה mikvah. *mikvah*. Now, will that
get me out of it? Well, it depends how long ago you're
saying I became טמא tamei *tamei*. If you said I became טמא
tamei? *tamei* yesterday, טומאה tumah. ישנה *tuma yeshana*, an old טומאה tumah,
*tuma*, and I say I didn't, and I ate a קרבן korban.
*korban* today, and I say I didn't become טמא tamei, *tamei*, it
could mean I didn't remain טמא tamei, *tamei*, I went to the
מקוה mikvah? *mikvah*. But if you said I became טמא tamei, *tamei*
today and I ate a קרבן korban, *korban* today and I say
I didn't become טמא tamei *tamei*, then what could it mean? Even
if I said I went to the מקוה mikvah, *mikvah*, since it's
not yet nightfall, I'm still טמא tamei. *tamei* and I would still
have to, and I would still have transgressed. So if the only
way we believe me is by reinterpreting my words, there's no way
to reinterpret them when it's about a טומאה tumah *tuma* today. Okay,
got that? If you say I didn't eat, we could say it
means I didn't eat במזיד bemezid. *bemezid*, I ate בשוגג beshogeg, *beshogeg*.
But if I say I didn't become טמא tamei, *tamei*, the only
way to reinterpret it in a way that gets me out of
it is by saying I didn't remain טמא tamei *tamei*, but that
can only be meaningful if it's about yesterday's טומאה tumah, *tuma*, not
today's טומאה tumah, *tuma*. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *gemara* says like
this. So it's a difference about טומאה tumah, *tuma*. If you said
I'm just believed more than the witnesses in this regard, it doesn't
matter old טומאה tumah. *tuma* or new טומאה tumah, *tuma*. ואי אמרת
טעמייהו דרבנן משום דאמרינן מיגו migo *ve'i amrat ta'ameihu derabbanan mishum de'amrinan
migo*, but if the reason of the Rabbis is because of מיגו
*migo*, and here we're saying מיגו *migo* really means because we're able
to reinterpret his words, he, פטרי ליה רבנן מטומאה ישנה *patrei lei
rabbanan mituma yeshana*, then if it's an old טומאה tumah *tuma* we
can get him out of it, we can say it means I
didn't remain טמא tamei *tamei*. אבל מטומאה חדשה *aval mituma chadasha*, but
if it's a new טומאה tum'ah, *tuma*, מחייב mechayev. *mechayav*, then I
would still have to bring a קרבן korban. *korban*. מאי mai, טעמא
*mai ta'ama*, what's the reason? טומאה tum'ah ישנה *tuma yeshana*, because an
old טומאה *tuma*, מיגו דאי בעי אמר טבלתי *migo de'i ba'ei amar
tavalti*, פטר *patar*, since you could have said I went to the
מקוה mikvah, *mikvah* you'd be exempt. כי אמר נמי לא נטמאתי lo
nitmeti, *ki amar nami lo nitmeisi*, even when you say you didn't
become טמא tamei. *tamei*, פטר *patar*, you're exempt, דאיכא למימר *de'ika lemeimar*,
that we can interpret to say, מאי לא נטמאתי lo nitmeiti, דקאמר
*mai lo nitmeisi deka'amar*, what does it mean I didn't become טמא
tamei. *tamei*? לא עמדתי בטומאתי lo amadeti betum'ati, *lo amadeti betumasi*, it
means I didn't remain טמא tamei, *tamei*, אלא טבלתי ela tavalti, *ela
tavalti*, but I went to the מקוה mikvah, *mikvah*. So there you
give us what to work with and we can reinterpret it to
mean I didn't remain טמא tamei. *tamei*. אבל טומאה חדשה *aval tuma
chadasha*, but if it's a טומאה *tuma* that came today, מחייב mechayev.
*mechayav*, then if the only way you get out of it is
by us helping you reinterpret your words. words, then you're stuck. מאי
טעמא? What's the reason? דכי אמר נמי טבלתי, d'ki amar nami tavalti,
מחייב. Even if you were to say I went to the מקווה
mikvah today you'd still be מחייב. דאמרו ליה עדים השתא נטמאת, d'amru
lei edim hashta nitmata, because they say to you now you became
טמא tamei and even if you would have said okay but I
went to the מקווה, mikvah, you're still going to have to, you
still have transgressed. So מאי, what's the rule? So again we have
two possibilities. One is forget the witnesses, they're irrelevant. And again as
I said it's because ultimately this is not about the court, it's
about you and God. The other is we can't completely ignore the
witnesses. We'll give you a lot of latitude, but we can't completely
ignore them, so you'll have to find a way to reinterpret your
statement. If there's no way to reinterpret your statement, then we're going
to have to go with the witnesses, then we're stuck. And that's
the question when they say you became טמא tamei, today and you
said I didn't become טמא, tamei, then you're stuck. There's no way
we can get you out of that. Yes. It would be the
same thing if they said you went through a graveyard and you
said no I didn't. You can't reinterpret that as... Yeah, I didn't
do, I didn't remain in the... well okay that's true if you
speak more about the action than about the state, maybe. And we'll
have some cases like that as well. Okay, let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara תא שמע, ta shema, come and hear. אמרו
לו עד אחד, amru lo ed echad, one witness said to him,
נטמאת, nitmeta, you became טמא, tamei, והוא אומר, vehu omer, and he
says, לא נטמאתי, lo nitmeiti, I did not become טמא, tamei, פטור,
patur, he is exempt. יכול אפילו שנים, yachol afilu shenayim, maybe even
two witnesses that you'd be exempt when you contradict that? אמר רבי
מאיר קל וחומר, amar Rabbi Meir kal vachomer, this is just like
our משנה Mishnah, except it's a ברייתא Braita and it's explicitly dealing
with the example of becoming טמא. tamei. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says
קל וחומר, kal vachomer, אם הביאו שנים למיתה חמורה, im heviu shenayim
lemita chamurah, if two witnesses can get you to the death penalty,
לא יביאו לידי קרבן הקל, lo yaveiu lidei korban hakal, how much
more so can they, you know, make you bring a קרבן? korban.
וחכמים אומרים, vachachamim omrim, and the חכמים Chachamim say no, אדם נאמן
על עצמו יותר ממאה איש, adam ne'eman al atzmo yoter mimeo ish,
a person is believed more than a hundred people. So here you
see, it seems like this ברייתא Braita is exactly our question. First
of all, the rabbis give their reason, not because we, not like
our משנה, Mishnah, right? Our משנה, Mishnah the reason was you could
have said מזיד. mezid. Our משנה Mishnah emphasized the idea of reinterpreting
your words as a possibility of other statements. Here it just says
you're believed more than witnesses. It's a straight idea that we care
about what you say, we don't care about what they say. The
other point is in addition to the reason given, the case is
about having become טמא. tamei, So it sounds like it's a case
where you really don't have any latitude to reinterpret the words, and
nevertheless we believe you more than the witnesses. It wouldn't work if
they said, you know, you borrowed a hundred dollars and you said
no I didn't, right? They wouldn't say that. Yes, they would. But
oh no, not borrowed. No, it's about קרבן. korban, It's all about
קרבן. korban. Okay, so you see שמע מינה, shma mina, we see
from this, טעמיה דרבנן משום דאדם נאמן על עצמו יותר ממאה איש,
taamei d'rabbanan mishum d'adam ne'eman al atzmo yoter mimeo ish, that the
reason is because we believe you more than witnesses, you know, categorically
when it comes to issues of קרבן. korban, A, because of again
the reason given, and B, because of the application to the case
of טומאה. אמר רב אמי, amar Rav Ami, said רב אמי, Rav
Ami, לעולם טעמיה דרבנן משום דאמרינן מיגו. le'olam taamei d'rabbanan mishum d'amrinan
migo. No, really it's because of מיגו and because of like reinterpreting
your words. והכי קתני, vehachi katani, and this is what it's teaching:
מתוך שאם רצה לומר לא עמדתי בטומאתי פטור, mitoch she'im ratza lomar
lo amadeti betumati patur, we'll assume that we're talking about an old
טומאה, not a new טומאה. So you could have got out of
it by saying what I didn't become טמא tamei, means I didn't
remain טמא, tamei I went to the מקווה. mikvah. Since you could
say that and be exempt, הלכך אדם נאמן על עצמו יותר ממאה
איש. hilkach adam ne'eman al atzmo yoter mimeo ish. Therefore you are
believed more than a hundred people. Meaning, yes, it's talking about טומאה,
but again, maybe it's talking about old טומאה. And old טומאה, when
you say I didn't become טמא, tamei, we are able to reinterpret
to mean I didn't remain טמא, tamei, I went to the מקווה.
mikvah. Ah, doesn't it say the reason is because you're believed more
than the witnesses? It doesn't mean you're categorically believed more than the
witnesses. It means here we'll believe you against the witnesses because we're
able to reinterpret your words. Okay? So it seemed to be a
proof that it was about categorically believing you because it was about
טומאה and it used that phrase that we just believe you more,
but it says no, maybe it's a case where it's an old
טומאה, we're believing you because we're able to reinterpret your words, and
when it says we believe you more, it means we're able to
believe you more in this case because in this case we're able
to reinterpret your words. Okay? But anyway, I will just take a
step back and say that you see here, you know, sometimes the
גמרא Gemara, raises a question and you think it's very theoretical and
abstract, you know, and it's like a new type of a question
that hadn't been asked before. Here what you really see is is
that the question the גמרא Gemara is phrasing is really emerging from
different types of tannaitic material. Our משנה Mishnah frames the rabbis' reasons
as saying because you could have said you were intentional, talks about
reframing what you could
have said, and this ברייתא Braita frames it about the fact that
fundamentally you're believed more.
So the גמרא's Gemara really trying, you know, question is really reflecting
the different types of tannaitic material here that expresses different reasons for
the חכמים. Chachamim. Okay, so let's see as the גמרא Gemara continues.
It says like this. Okay, where are we? אי הכי, ei hachi,
says the גמרא, Gemara היינו חלב. hainu chelev. So if that's true
that it's just telling me we can reinterpret your words, then why
do you need to tell me this case of the ברייתא? Braita?
It's exactly like the classic case in our משנה Mishna, about eating
forbidden fat. Presumably if we're giving you this other case about becoming
טמא, tamei, it's to show you that we can take it even
further. Otherwise it's just like the case in the ברייתא. Braita. So
the גמרא Gemara says no. מהו דתימא אכלתי חלב קמתרצי דיבוריה, mahu
deteima achalti chelev kamatretzi diburei, לא אכלתי שוגג אלא מזיד. lo achalti
shogeg ela mezid. No, I would have said... (Wait, I'll stop here).
*Final check on "Rabbi Yehuda":* "רבי יהודה אומר". Rabbi Yehuda omer *Final
check on "Tosafot":* "תוספות Tosafot takes this so far". *Final check on
"Ta shema":* "תא שמע, Ta shema, come and hear." *Final check on
"Vehitvada":* "והתודה, Vehitvada, and he shall atone." *Final check on "modeh bidvarim
chayav":* "והתודה, Vehitvada, מודה בדברים חייב." modeh bidvarim chayav. *Final check on
"Ein modeh bidvarim patur":* "אין מודה בדברים פטור." Ein modeh bidvarim patur.
*Final check on "Yakhol afilu shnayim machishin":* "יכול אפילו שנים מכחישין". Yakhol
afilu shnayim machishin *Final check on "im heviu shnayim lidei misa chamura
lo yeviu lidei korban hakal":* "אם הביאו שנים לידי מיתה חמורה לא
יביאו לידי קרבן הקל". im heviu shnayim lidei misa chamura lo yeviu
lidei korban hakal *Final check on "Aval nitmatei":* "אבל נטמאתי, Aval nitmatei,
but if you say". *Final check on "Eima lo kametartz diburei":* "אימא
לא קמתרץ דיבוריה, Eima lo kametartz diburei, maybe we can't". *Final check
on "kamashma lan":* "קא משמע לן kamashma lan that we can". *Final
check on "Hacha nami lo amadeti betumati":* "הכא נמי לא עמדתי בטומאתי,
Hacha nami lo amadeti betumati, it means". *Final check on "aval tavalti":*
"אבל טבלתי, aval tavalti, I went". *Final check on "Amru lo ed
echad nitmeita":* "אמרו ליה עד אחד נטמאת". Amlei ed echad d'itmeisa *Final
check on "Vehu omer lo nitmeisi":* "והוא אומר לא נטמאתי". Vehu omer
lo nitmeisi *Final check on "Patur":* "פטור, Patur, you're exempt." *Final check
on "pshat":* "פשט pshat explicit". *Final check on "chatas":* "קרבן חטאת". korban
chatas *Final check on "teshuvah":* "תשובה teshuvah process". *Final check on "vidui":*
"וידוי, vidui, of confession." *Final check on "pasuk":* "פסוק pasuk of והתודה".
vehitvada *Final check on "Gemara":* "גמרא Gemara is also quoting". *Final check
on "edim":* "two עדים edim said". *Final check on "hachelev":* "gam את
החלב". et hachelev *Final check on "hadam":* "וגם את הדם". vegam et
hadam *Final check on "hagezel":* "וגם את הגזל". vegam et hagezel *Final
check on "korban":* "bring a קרבן." korban, *Final check on "beshogeg":* "come
בשוגג." b'shogeg, *Final check on "bemazid":* "even במזיד". b'meizid, *Final check on
"Rabbi Meir":* "אמר רבי מאיר". Amar Rabbi Meir *Final check on "Rabbi
Yehuda":* "רבי יהודה אומר". Rabbi Yehuda omer *Final check on "Tosafot":* "תוספות
Tosafot takes this so far". *Final check on "Ta shema":* "תא שמע,
Ta shema, come and hear." *Final check on "Vehitvada":* "והתודה, Vehitvada, and
he shall atone." *Final check on "modeh bidvarim chayav":* "והתודה, Vehitvada, מודה
בדברים חייב." modeh bidvarim chayav. *Final check on "Ein modeh bidvarim patur":*
"אין מודה בדברים פטור." Ein modeh bidvarim patur. *Final check on "Yakhol
afilu shnayim machishin":* "יכול אפילו שנים מכחישין". Yakhol afilu shnayim machishin *Final
check on "im heviu shnayim lidei misa chamura lo yeviu lidei korban
hakal":* "אם הביאו שנים לידי מיתה חמורה לא יביאו לידי קרבן הקל".
im heviu shnayim lidei misa chamura lo yeviu lidei korban hakal *Final
check on "Aval nitmatei":* "אבל נטמאתי, Aval nitmatei, but if you say".
*Final check on "Eima lo kametartz diburei":* "אימא לא קמתרץ דיבוריה, Eima
lo kametartz diburei, maybe we can't". *Final check on "kamashma lan":* "קא
משמע לן kamashma lan that we can". *Final check on "Hacha nami
lo amadeti betumati":* "הכא נמי לא עמדתי בטומאתי, Hacha nami lo amadeti
betumati, it means". *Final check on "aval tavalti":* "אבל טבלתי, aval tavalti,
I went". *Final check on "Amru lo ed echad nitmeita":* "אמרו ליה
עד אחד נטמאת". Amlei ed echad d'itmeisa *Final check on "Vehu omer
lo nitmeisi":* "והוא אומר לא נטמאתי". Vehu omer lo nitmeisi *Final check
on "Patur":* "פטור, Patur, you're exempt." *Final check on "pshat":* "פשט pshat
explicit". *Final check on "chatas":* "קרבן חטאת". korban chatas *Final check on
"teshuvah":* "תשובה teshuvah process". *Final check on "vidui":* "וידוי, vidui, of confession."
*Final check on "pasuk":* "פסוק pasuk of והתודה". vehitvada *Final check on
"Gemara":* "גמרא Gemara is also quoting". *Final check on "edim":* "two עדים
edim said". *Final check on "hachelev":* "gam את החלב". et hachelev *Final
check on "hadam":* "וגם את הדם". vegam et hadam *Final check on
"hagezel":* "וגם את הגזל". vegam et hagezel *Final check on "korban":* "bring
a קרבן." korban *Final check on "beshogeg":* "come בשוגג." *Final check on
"bemazid":* "even במזיד". b'meizid *Final check on "Rabbi Meir":* "אמר רבי מאיר".
Amar Rabbi Meir *Final check on "Rabbi Yehuda":* "רבי יהודה אומר". Rabbi
Yehuda omer *Final check on "Tosafot":* "תוספות Tosafot takes this so far".
*Final check on "Ta shema":* "תא שמע, Ta shema, come and hear."
*Final check on "Vehitvada":* "והתודה, Vehitvada, and he shall atone." *Final check
on "modeh bidvarim chayav":* "והתודה, Vehitvada, מודה בדברים חייב." modeh bidvarim chayav.
*Final check on "Ein modeh bidvarim patur":* "אין מודה בדברים פטור." Ein
modeh bidvarim patur. *Final check on "Yakhol afilu shnayim machishin":* "יכול אפילו
שנים מכחישין". Yakhol afilu shnayim machishin *Final check on "im heviu shnayim
lidei misa chamura lo yeviu lidei korban hakal":* "אם הביאו שנים לידי
מיתה חמורה לא יביאו לידי קרבן הקל". im heviu shnayim lidei misa
chamura lo yeviu lidei korban hakal *Final check on "Aval nitmatei":* "אבל
נטמאתי, Aval nitmatei, but if you say". *Final check on "Eima lo
kametartz diburei":* "אימא לא קמתרץ דיבוריה, Eima lo kametartz diburei, maybe we
can't". *Final check on "kamashma lan":* "קא משמע לן kamashma lan that
we can". *Final check on "Hacha nami lo amadeti betumati":* "הכא נמי
לא עמדתי בטומאתי, Hacha nami lo amadeti betumati, it means". *Final check
on "aval tavalti":* "אבל טבלתי, aval tavalti, I went". *Final check on
"Amru lo ed ech by the person who did it. And actually
it's worth noting, you know, that the תורה Torah does, although it
talks about doing וידוי viduy and confession and becoming aware, the concept
of תשובה teshuva is absent from the whole ויקרא Vayikra where it
talks about קרבנות. korbanot. You know, תשובה teshuva primarily comes up, you
know, in דברים Devarim where it talks about, you know, that's the
whole נצבים, Nitzavim, וילך, Vayelech, the stuff that we read right before
ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, okay? But in ויקרא, Vayikra, the atonement of
sins is through קרבנות, korbanot, not through תשובה. teshuva. So you can
try to read the התוודה hitvada and והודה לו hoda lo as
that process of תשובה teshuva expressed through the bringing of a קרבן,
korban but that's not necessarily what is at the forefront. So I
think רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir could be saying it's not about תשובה,
teshuva, it's about rectifying the sin in some metaphysical way, and therefore
even if you deny it, if we know it as a fact,
you have to bring it. And the חכמים Chachamim say no, it's
still about you owning up to it. That's just classic Yif- what
Edan would say. I understand, I'm trying to explain it conceptually. רבי
יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda Omer, so that's רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir רבי
יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda Omer, נאמן אדם על עצמו יותר ממאה איש.
ne'eman adam al atzmo yoter me'ah ish. So here it's out again
like the categorical statement. You're believed about yourself when it comes to
קרבנות korbanot issue. You say you didn't do it, you don't bring
a קרבן. korban. Now we have a middle position. ומודים חכמים לרבי
יהודה, Umodim Chachamim l'Rabbi Yehuda, there's a third חכמים Chachamim that we
haven't seen yet that agree to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda בחלבים ובביאת
מקדש. b'chalavim u'v'biat mikdash. When it comes to eating fat or going
into the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash? that you say you didn't do
it, then we'll believe you. אבל בטומאה לא מודי ליה. Aval b'tumah
lo modi lei. But if they say witnesses you became טמא tamei.
and you say you did not, they don't agree to him. And
there they would say you bring the קרבן. korban. Now what's the
difference between if you say I didn't eat fat, I didn't eat
the קרבן, korban. or you say I didn't become טמא? tamei, The
only difference is what we've said until now, that in the case
of I didn't eat fat, I didn't go into the בית המקדש,
Beit HaMikdash we can reinterpret your words. I didn't eat it בשוגג,
I only ate it במזיד, b'meizid, okay? Which means reinterpret it so
you don't bring a קרבן. korban, If you say I didn't become
טמא, tamei, maybe there's not the same latitude to reinterpret your words.
And therefore what it seems now is that there are really all
possibilities, right? Here in this ברייתא baraita you have all three possibilities.
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says we always believe the witnesses. רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda says we always believe you. It's about you and God,
not about the witnesses. And this middle position of the חכמים Chachamim
that says we'll believe you if we can reinterpret your words. But
if there's no way to reinterpret your words, then we're going to
have to go with the witnesses. So when it comes to fat
and eating the קרבן, korban, we can reinterpret your words to say
you only you did it במזיד. When it comes to becoming טמא,
tamei. we really don't have that much latitude to reinterpret your words,
and therefore we'll go with the witnesses. So the question the גמרא
Gemara asks is really the two opinions of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
and the חכמים. Chachamim. And now the גמרא Gemara just wraps this
up, okay? לא מודי ליה. Lo modi lei. במאי עסקינן? B'mai askeinan?
What are we talking about? אילימא דטומאה ישנה, Ileima d'tumah yeshana, if
it's an old טומאה, then we should be able to reinterpret your
words like we said before. מאי שנא חלבים וביאת מקדש דמודי ליה?
Mai shna chalavim u'viat mikdash d'modi lei? Why do they agree by
the cases of fat and entering into the בית המקדש? Beis HaMikdash
דאם רצה אמר מזיד הייתי, D'im ratza amar meizid hayiti, you could
have said I did it intentionally and therefore we'll reinterpret your words
to mean that. So טומאה ישנה נמי, tumah yeshana nami, so even
if it's an old טומאה, מתרץ דיבוריה, metaretz diburei, let's reinterpret your
words. דאם ירצה יאמר לא עמדתי בטומאתי אלא טבלתי, D'im yirtza yomar
lo amadeti b'tumati ela tavalti, that you can say I did not
become טמא, tamei rather I went to the מקוה. mikvah. So implicitly
therefore, the end of the statement is implicitly we're talking about a
new טומאה. And a new טומאה, there's no way to reinterpret your
words, right? They say you became טמא tamei. and went into the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash. today. You say I didn't become טמא. tamei.
What are we going to reinterpret it to mean? I didn't remain
טמא, tamei, I went to the מקוה? mikvah But it all happened
today. Even if you went to the מקוה, mikvah you would still
have sin. So that's what we're saying now. That רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir says you always go by the witnesses, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
says you always go by what you say, and a middle position
so that's נאמן יותר ממאה איש, ne'eman yoter me'ah ish, and a
middle position of the חכמים Chachamim that says that we'll go by
what you say if we can reinterpret your words in a way
that works, which often will almost always work. But if the עדים
eidim say you became טמא tamei today and you say no I
didn't, then you're not giving us any latitude here, right? Because what
can we interpret those words to mean? Even if they mean you
went to the מקוה, mikvah, you still have transgressed. And that's for
those are the range of opinions. Yes. What type of טומאה are
they talking about? טומאת מת, tumah met, stepping on a שרץ? sheretz?
Wouldn't a person know more than the witnesses? Not necessarily. I mean
it could exactly be like stepping on a שרץ sheretz and you
didn't see it. So you could say I didn't step on it,
my foot I saw it and I picked up my foot at
the last minute, or it was dead already and I didn't kill
it, I didn't step on- I mean wouldn't a person or I
got close to the corpse but didn't touch it? Yeah, wouldn't a
person know more than- himself would know, it doesn't matter how many
witnesses. Yeah, but so that's- I mean but in the end that's
sort of saying that, you know, what you're really saying is not
that we- well, what you're really saying is that let us suspect
that the witnesses actually have made a mistake. And, you know, normally
the way we try to determine that is by cross-examining the witnesses.
You know, and we'll say to the witnesses, are you sure, do
you Know that it was dead already, did you see him touch
it and so on, but to go actually say after we've done
our job as cross-examining the witnesses that we're still going to suspect
that this guy sort of knows more than you, and in a
normal court case we wouldn't say it. Meaning, let's say it wasn't
what was special about this, that it's about you and God and
a קרבן, korban, right? Let's say it was about, you know, witnesses
testified that I borrowed a hundred dollars and I said I didn't.
But that's different, someone else... I understand, I understand. So in the
end I'm agreeing with you. What you're essentially saying is, let's be
prepared to believe you because at the end of the day it's
between you and God. So you know what? That is what we
say. The only question is how far do we take that? So
one opinion there is נאמן על עצמו יותר ממאה איש. We'll take
it to the extreme, even if there's no latitude in terms of
you, you know, it's blatant that you're contradicting the witnesses, but nevertheless
it's just between you and God. The middle position is essentially what
you're saying. So what the גמרא Gemara is saying, no, we'll try
to make it work. The גמרא Gemara is saying we'll try to
make it work by reinterpreting your statement to work. You're saying let's
try to make it work by finding fault in what the witnesses
are saying. But in the end, you know, it's the same point.
We are going to try to believe you because ultimately it's between
you and God, and let's find a way that you're not really
contradicting the witnesses. So I think the גמרא Gemara would rather find
that way by reinterpreting your statement than by actually casting doubts into
the testimony of witnesses, because we normally want to accept the weight
of the testimony of witnesses. We don't want to start being skeptical
about it. But it's the same basic approach. Okay, so that... so
now the גמרא Gemara just has one last statement of רבינא, Ravina,
which is a little bit difficult to understand, but let's read it.
So and there's a whole question as you might imagine about גירסא
girsa and whatever, but whatever. אמר רבינא, Amar Ravina, לעולם בטומאה ישנה.
le'olam betum'ah yeshanah. You have tried to implicitly say that this is
talking about a new טומאה, and the reason this middle position of
the חכמים Chachamim don't believe you is because there's no room to
reinterpret because they say you became טמא tamei today. I will give
you a scenario where it's old טומאה and we also can't reinterpret
your words. Why not? Let's take a look. לעולם בטומאה ישנה, le'olam
betum'ah yeshanah, כגון דאמרי ליה עדים, kegon de'amri leh edim, witnesses say
to you, אכלת קדשים בטומאת הגוף. achalta kodashim betum'at haguf. They emphasize
not the fact that you became טמא. tamei, The emphasis of their
testimony is that you ate a קרבן korban in the context of
the fact that you were טמא. tamei. So they say you ate
a קרבן korban, when you were טמא, tamei but their emphasis is
you ate a קרבן. korban והוא אמר להון, vehu amar lehon, and
you try to undercut the assumption of their testimony, לא נטמאתי, lo
nitmeiti I didn't eat a... I wasn't טמא. tamei, Now why don't
we say מתרצינן דיבוריה? metartzinan diburei? What's מתרצינן דיבוריה? metartzinan diburei? It
means לא נטמאתי, Lo nitmeisi לא עמדתי בטומאתי, lo amadeti betum'ati I
went to the מקוה, mikvah. etc. Why can't we say the same
thing here? So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. דהכא לא
מתרצינן דיבוריה, dehacha lo metartzinan diburei, we can't reinterpret your word. Why
not? דליכא למימר deleika lemeimar לא עמדתי בטומאתי אלא טבלתי, you can't
say I didn't remain טמא tamei, but I went to the מקוה.
mikvah מאי אמר להון? mai amar lehon? טבלתי ואכלתי. tavalti ve'achalti. Because
then implicitly they said you ate when you were טמא, tamei. and
what you would be saying is, you said I wasn't טמא, tamei,
but the only way we can reinterpret it to give you some
strength to your claim is, no, you misunderstood, I had already gone
to the מקוה mikvah. and then I had eaten. לא נטמאתי meaning
I didn't remain טמא, tamei. I had been to the מקוה mikvah,
and then I ate. Then you wouldn't be contradicting them and you
would still get off the hook for a קרבן. korban So why
can't we reinterpret it that way? כי אמר להון הכי, ki amar
lehon hachi, because if you were to say that, that I went
to the מקוה, mikvah. איתכחש ליה דיבוריה קמא מיהו בטומאת מגע, itkashleh
diburei kama mihu betum'at maga, you would be contradicting your original statement
about becoming טמא, tamei. because originally you said you didn't become טמא.
tamei, What does this mean? It's a strange idea anyway and I
mean, but anyway I'll just explain it, I'm not going to work
to defend it because I myself am bothered by it, but here's
the concept. The concept is the following. Normally you made a statement,
we reinterpret the statement you made. You said I did not become
טמא, tamei, they said you became טמא, tamei, you said I didn't
become טמא tamei, and we reinterpret to mean I didn't remain טמא,
tamei I went to the מקוה. They said you ate, you say
I didn't eat, what you mean to say is you didn't eat...
I didn't eat בשוגג, I ate במזיד. We reinterpret your basic statement.
Here the problem is, the assumption is, is that we have to
formulate a statement that
is in direct response to the witnesses. You know like they do
on those like lawyer shows, you know, non-responsive answer? So you can't
give a non-responsive answer. So if they say you ate, you know,
when you were טמא, tamei your answer has to be about eating.
Now you could say, yes I ate but I wasn't טמא, tamei
yes I ate but I went to the מקוה or something like
that, but it has to directly respond to what they say. Instead
you didn't directly respond. You said I wasn't טמא. tamei. That's seen
as non-responsive. I know, it doesn't sound as non-responsive as it sounds,
I wasn't טמא, tamei but that we have to reinterpret that to
create a statement that directly responds to them. So you say you
ate when you were טמא, tamei. you said I wasn't טמא. What
statement really responds to them? You know, when I ate I had
already gone to the מקוה. That will sort of be the statement
that will have responded to them. So that is seen as a
new statement, not a reinterpretation of the old. The old one wasn't
addressing them directly and therefore we have to create a new statement.
If that's what your response to them is, then it's contradicting your
original statement that you weren't טמא because here you're saying I went
to the מקוה, which means I was טמא. So this is like
a very weird idea that within this idea that we're going to
reinterpret your word, if we have to create a new type of
a statement, then we haven't really reinterpreted these old words and then
you're in
contradiction. So that doesn't give us the latitude to reinterpret your words.
Okay, it seems very technical, but we'll just accept that that's a
way רבינא Ravina understands that there are sometimes we can't reinterpret your
word. At the end of the day though, we have the two
positions, we have the three positions. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that says
it's a straight case, you go by witnesses. Two positions in the
response. One is, it's all about you and God, forget witnesses. And
the other middle position is, if there's no way out of it,
we'll go by the witnesses, but we will try as much as
possible to reinterpret what you said in order that we can go
by what you said and not by what the witnesses say.
Yes. By the it's all between you and God, maybe position there's
an issue of we have to permit you to give a חטאת
chatat in order to. Right, you could frame it that way. I
think somebody, I think תוספות Tosafot might have said that one place,
which is also that if you're insisting that
you're not חייב, chayav, then by us trying to force you to
bring, we're essentially, you're saying you're telling me to bring חולין בעזרה.
chullin ba'azarah. Right, right, you know, so you could like reframe it
that way as well. I think תוספות Tosafot raises that issue as
well. תוספות Tosafot also says, you know, there's also a question about
look, תוספות Tosafot also says what does all of this matter if
we פוסקין poskin in ערכין Arachin that we're not going to force
you to bring a חטאת. chatat. So here's what conclusion we come
to here at the end of the day, we're not going to
force you to do it anyway because even if we say you're
חייב. chayav. So תוספות Tosafot tries to say, well, maybe we won't
force you if you admit you're חייב chayav and you just say
you don't want to bring it. But if you deny that you're
חייב chayav and we've decided you are, maybe we will force you.
But anyway, it all goes around that point that maybe this is
not something we're going to in the end of the day get
mixed up in. And your point is also good. You could say
either you're forcing me to do a sin. Okay, so let's take
a look. Now we're going to, now that we've laid out those
positions, we're going to talk about הלכה halachah and cases where even
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir might agree that we put the witnesses aside.
Let's take a look. אמר רב נחמן הלכה כרבי יהודה. Amar Rav
Nachman halachah k'Rabbi Yehuda. We rule like רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. Now
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is the one that said the extreme version
that you're believed more than a hundred witnesses. It's totally about you
and God, not about the witnesses. Okay. אמר רב יוסף לא אמרה
אלא בינו לבין עצמו ולעצמו. Amar Rav Yosef lo amrah ela beino
l'vein atzmo u'l'atzmo. So meaning, so you only, it's only when it's
between you doing it between you and yourself. What does that mean?
So the way רש"י Rashi explains it is that you said you
didn't become טמא. Okay, now you are going to and we, however
we reinterpret it, I didn't remain טמא, blah, blah, blah. Now you
are going to go ahead and eat תרומה terumah or eat a
קרבן. korban. Everybody else has heard the witnesses testify. This is sort
of like Michael's question, which is, it's one thing to say we
believe you for a קרבן, korban. but there are other consequences implicit
in your statement. If they said you became טמא and entered the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash, and you say I don't become טמא and
we say okay, we'll totally believe you, don't bring a קרבן, korban.
this is between you and God. But if I'm saying I'm not
טמא, it also means that if I go ahead and touch Michael's
תרומה, terumah, you know, that it's also not טמא. Maybe for that
we do believe the witnesses because that's no longer about my sin
and me and God, that's about the question of whether I'm טמא
and what are the implications if I touch other things, right? Is
that clear? Meaning when there's, by believing me, we could believe me
vis-a-vis the קרבן, korban but how much do we believe me vis-a-vis
the other implications of what I have done? So that's where the
גמרא Gemara says here that it's only when it's between you and
yourself. בינו לבין עצמו ולעצמו, Beino l'vein atzmo u'l'atzmo, between you and
yourself and for yourself. So which means number one, רש"י Rashi explains
this in two ways. בינו לבין עצמו Beino l'vein atzmo means don't
go ahead and, I shouldn't come here after having this little fight
with the witnesses and we believed me and I'm going to come
ahead with all of you and I'm going to take out my
תרומה terumah food and eat it in front of you because you
will have heard the witnesses, you're going to believe that I'm טמא,
you're going to see me eating תרומה terumah even though you believe
that I'm טמא, so that's going to, you know, undermine the seriousness
of eating תרומה בטומאה terumah b'tumah because you're believing the witnesses, you're
not believing me because you heard witnesses say I was טמא. So
that's if I'm going to eat תרומה, terumah, I should do it
in private. That's בינו לבין עצמו. Beino l'vein atzmo. And ולעצמו u'l'atzmo
means like I said before, if I want to go ahead and
now touch my תרומה terumah and eat my תרומה, terumah, that's again
between me and God. I say I'm טהור, tahor, witnesses say I'm
טמא, as long as they're not going to give me lashes, you
know, as long as nobody else is seeing and I'm just going
to do it in private if I know I'm טהור, tahor, it's
between me and God. But it doesn't mean I can go ahead
and touch Michael's תרומה, terumah, right? And he can now eat it,
right? I'm believed for my own issues, I'm not believed for. What
if Michael touches it? You would have to be, yeah, you'd have
to believe the witnesses. Okay, so this is really quite a fascinating
idea, right? Because when it comes, we believe me because at the
end of the day my sin is between me and God. If
I didn't do it במזיד, if I did it במזיד then בית
דין Beis Din has to get involved, right? But it's between me
and God. So therefore I don't bring a קרבן korban if I.
Nobody is watching I can go ahead and eat my תרומה, trumah,
okay, and do whatever I want to do because I'm saying I'm
not טמא. But I can't do it in a way that has
an impact on the larger society because they're listening to the witnesses.
So I can't do it visibly because then that's going to undermine
the seriousness of it for them, eating the תרומה trumah and whatever,
and I can't and if I touch other people's תרומה, trumah, well
that's a case of היזק ניכר hezek nikar anyway, there are implications.
Michael can't eat the תרומה trumah that I touched. Michael has to
believe the witnesses. He can't believe me. Okay, so that's really interesting.
Yeah, what? And if you eat it in the shul then what?
I mean, what happens? If you eat it in the shul? Like
you said right now, like you come here and you start eating
your תרומה trumah in front of me. Right. No, that's just a
question about that's not proper because it's undermining it because you're believing
the witnesses and here I am blatantly violating in your presence. Now
the interesting point would be, I can eat the תרומה trumah in
my home because I know I'm טהור tahor regardless of what the
witnesses say, but if witnesses watch me eat it and give me
התראה, hasra'ah, they can give me lashes in בית דין, beis din,
right? So for things that are objective, which means both punishments, which
is not just between me and God, punishments for sins, which is
a matter of בית דין, beis din, or for other people, we
have to go by the objective evidence of the witnesses. Things that
remain between me and God in the privacy of my home and
bringing a קרבן, korban that I'm able to do what I know
is the truth. Quite a fascinating idea, yes. So, I believe the
witnesses, this person comes and touches my תרומה, trumah, I now have
to burn it? Yes. Wow. Yeah, exactly. So that's you know, even
but if he were a כהן kohen and I gave it to
him before he touched it, he could eat it. Exactly. That's what
the גמרא Gemara, says. You're allowed to give it to that כהן.
kohen. You're assuming? Well, you you'll he'll always become טהור. tahor. He
can always go to the מקוה. Okay, anyway, presumably, I mean the
statement is not fully fleshed out, but so it's a real question
of what to read in exactly the parameters of those words, but
that is trying to point to this fascinating idea that it's a
question about things that are between you and God and things that
impact other people. Okay, so now what? What? Touching it then. All
right, you were about to give it to this guy. Okay, let's
see what the גמרא Gemara says. Maybe it's not הוחזק כפרן. huchzak
kafran. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר
ריש לקיש, Amar Reish Lakish, מודה רבי מאיר לחכמים, modeh Rabbi Meir
l'chachamim, here are ways in which רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir would agree
to the חכמים chachamim that we would not go by the witnesses.
שאם אמרו לו שנים בעלת שפחה חרופה, She'im amru lo shnayim ba'alta
shifcha charufa, two witnesses say that you had sex with this שפחה
חרופה, shifcha charufa, half-freed slave we talked about yesterday, והוא אומר לא
בעלתי, v'hu omer lo ba'alti, and you say you didn't, מהימן, meheman,
you're believed. Why? Why would he be believed? דאי בעי אמר להון
לא גמרתי ביאתי, D'iba'i amar lehon lo gamarti bi'ati, because he says
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir actually would agree that he'd be prepared to
reinterpret your words. The only reason he's not prepared to reinterpret your
words in the other cases is because A, they make you look
worse, like you say I didn't do it בשוגג, I did it
במזיד, or because it's very far-fetched. לא נטמאתי means I didn't remain
טמא. But if we can reinterpret your words in a reasonable way
that makes you even look better, then we will. So remember we
say by a שפחה חרופה shifcha charufa that the only act that
you're חייב chayav in a קרבן korban is when it is ביאה,
bi'ah, it's גמר ביאה, gmar bi'ah, full penetration. So whatever, yes, so
if you if they say you you had ביאה bi'ah and you
say I didn't, what you could really mean is I didn't do
it fully. And if you didn't do it fully, you wouldn't be
חייב. chayav. So that actually makes you look better, not worse, and
it's a reasonable reinterpretation, so there are cases רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir
would be prepared to allow you to reinterpret your words. אמר רב
ששת, Amar Rav Sheshet, said רב ששת, Rav Sheshet, מודה רבי מאיר
לחכמים, modeh Rabbi Meir l'chachamim, here's another case he would agree to
the חכמים. chachamim. בנזיר טמא, B'nazir tamei, a נזיר nazir who was
טמא, שאמרו לו שנים נטמאת, she'amru lo shnayim nitmeisa, you became טמא,
and then he has to bring a קרבן korban? for a נזיר
nazir who became טמא, והוא אומר לא נטמאתי, v'hu omer lo nitmeisi,
פטור, patur, that he is exempt. Why? דאי בעי אמר נשאלתי על
נזיראי, D'iba'i amar nish'alti al nezirai, because he could have said that
I, you know, went ahead and had my whole נזירות nezirus undone.
Now big deal, at the end of the day, you're still contradicting
the witnesses. Is רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir, saying that if you have
a really good alternative way of getting out of it, we'll believe
you against the witnesses? Or maybe what he's really saying is is
that when you say I did not become טמא, what you really
are saying is, you know, I did not it was not a
case of a נזיר nazir who became טמא because I actually was
no longer a נזיר. nazir. Okay, it's a little bit funny because
it doesn't sound like you're really saying you're no longer a נזיר,
nazir, there would be other implications to saying you're no longer a
נזיר. nazir. But so that's a little bit that's a little strange.
That seems to be that there are real cases that if you
have a good a really good alternative, you would even beat out
witnesses. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, said אביי, Abaye, מודה רבי מאיר לחכמים,
modeh Rabbi Meir l'chachamim, here's another case רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir agrees
to the חכמים. chachamim. שאם אמרו לו שנים יודע אתה בעדות פלוני,
She'im amru lo shnayim yode'a ata b'eidus ploni, והוא אומר לא ידעתי,
v'hu omer lo yadati, פטור. patur. One of the cases of a
קרבן עולה ויורד korban oleh v'yored is that somebody makes you swear
that you don't know testimony to come to help him in court
and you swear and you're lying. And if witnesses actually come and
say, you know, you actually did know testimony to that guy, and
you said I didn't, that you actually would not have to bring
a קרבן. korban Why not? דאי בעי אמר לא נתכוונתי לעדות. D'iba'i
amar lo niskavanti l'eidus. The גמרא Gemara in מכות Makkot and other
places says that even if you saw something, if you didn't intend
to... to serve in the future as a witness, your testimony would
not be accepted in court. So even if the witnesses are saying
you actually are lying, you know testimony, and he's saying I don't
know testimony, we would believe you because I don't know testimony means
my testimony wouldn't have been accepted because I would because I never
intended to be a witness. This is a רישא שמא כולה, reisha
shema kula, right? Is that what you're talking about? Yeah. It does
work because you swore falsely, they're saying you swore falsely, you knew
testimony, and you're saying I did not know usable testimony. Okay, so
anyway, the point about this at the end, bracketing the נזיר Nazir
case, is that the גמרא, Gemara you know, is sort of is
saying that even רבי מאיר in some cases would be prepared to
work with what you said over what the witnesses said if we
could reasonably reinterpret what you said. Okay, but anyway, the basic structure
is as we said, three positions: רבי מאיר, we basically always go
with the witnesses except maybe in one or two cases where you've
given us something to work with; רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda that says
it's all between you and God; and the middle case, which is
we'd like to believe you, let's see if we can work with
what you said. Okay, and the real fascinating point that the וורט
vort said that if it's between you and God, what are the
implications for the rest of society based on that sort of, you
know, based on what you said and the חכמים Chachamim say. Now
we move to the second part
of the משנה, Mishna. which is how many קרבנות korbanos do you
bring? And if you basically eat multiple the same sin multiple times
in one state of forgetfulness, חלב וחלב, cheilev v'cheilev, you bring one
קרבן. korban. If you do different sins in the same state of
forgetfulness, you bring multiple קרבנות. korbanos. We've been saying this since the
beginning of the מסכת. masechet. Let's take a look. אכל חלב וחלב
בהעלם אחת. achal cheilev v'cheilev b'he'elam achas. So מתיב, maseiv, מתיב ליה
רב זירא. maseiv lei Rav Zeira. רב זירא Rav Zeira asked of
this. אמאי אינו חייב אלא חטאת אחת? amai eino chayav ela chatas
achas? Why if you eat multiple fats are you only one sin
offering? והא כזיתי חלב אכל. v'ha kezaysei cheilev achal. You ate two
כזיתים. kezaysim. He thinks that the fact that you did two sins,
even of the same genre, should mean two חטאות. chataos. אמר ליה
אביי. amar lei Abaye. So אביי Abaye said back to him, העלמות
מחולקות. he'elamos mecholakos. No, forgetfulness, different forgetfulnesses divide the sin. So if
you, I'm so, והכא העלם אחד הוא. v'hacha he'elam echad hu. You
need an act of forgetfulness to divide the sin. In one state
of forgetfulness, it is only one big eating of חלב. cheilev. Now
I should say interestingly that there is a similar parallel about the
question about getting lashes. Let's say witnesses say don't eat that piece
of חלב cheilev and you eat, and then you keep on eating
and you eat a hundred כזיתים. kezaysim. You're only going to get
one set of lashes. It's just like you ate a lot, right?
If a כזית, kezayis, here's another way of thinking about it also.
Is a כזית kezayis a minimum or does a כזית kezayis define
different acts? Right? If you tried, you did one act of eating.
What defines that act? Well, at least you had a כזית. kezayis.
But a hundred things is not a hundred acts, it's still one
act. It's one act once you've passed the minimum of a כזית.
kezayis. But doing a hundred כזיתים kezaysim doesn't mean a hundred acts.
That's another way of thinking about it. Anyway, if you have only
one warning, you get one set of lashes. The only way you'll
get multiple sets of lashes is if between each זית zayis they
tell you don't eat again, you'll get lashes, and you eat. Don't
eat and you'll get lashes,
and that redefines it as multiple acts.
Similarly here, if in one state of forgetfulness you eat a hundred
כזיתים, kezaysim, one sin, one קרבן. korban The only thing that defines
them as separate sins is if you remember in between, oh my
gosh, you know, it was חלב, cheilev, and then somehow you forgot
again and then you ate again. That will define them as separate,
otherwise it's one big thing. Okay, איכא, ika, now the גמרא Gemara
says the same point in just going from the opposite direction. דאיכא
דמתני לה הכי. d'ika d'masni lah hachi. Some ask it this way.
טעמא דהעלם אחת. ta'ama d'he'elam achas. The reason is because it's one
state of forgetfulness. הא בשתי העלמות חייב שתים. ha b'shtei he'elamos chayav
shtayim. If it's two states, you're חייב chayav two. אמאי? amai? שם
חלב אחד הוא. shem cheilev echad hu. The question was the opposite
way. Even if you remember and forget, why don't we just say
it's one big act? אמר ליה אביי העלמות מחולקות. amar lei Abaye
he'elamos mecholakos. No, if you if you remember in between, it defines
it as a separate act. So on the one hand, if you
don't remember in between, even if you do a large quantity, we'll
say it's one. If you remember in between, even though it's all
fat, nevertheless remembering and forgetting defines them as separate acts. Okay, so
that's if it is the same thing done with larger amounts. Now
אכל חלב ודם ופיגול ונותר חייב. achal cheilev v'dam u'pigul v'nosar chayav.
If however you do multiple sins in one state of forgetfulness, multiple
different objects, then you bring multiple קרבנות. korbanos. So the גמרא Gemara
says and it ends and it says okay, that's one thing. Then
it's now moving on to the end of the משנה. Mishna The
end of the משנה Mishnah says here's a way though where the
same type of a sin leads to more חיוב. chiyuv. If you
eat half a כזית kezayis and half a כזית kezayis of חלב,
cheilev, then you bring a קרבן korban. because you ate a whole
כזית. kezayis. If you eat a half a כזית kezayis of דם
dam and half a כזית kezayis of חלב, cheilev, you don't bring
a קרבן because you never ate a full כזית. kezayis. ממין אחד,
mimin echad, one genre, you bring a קרבן if it's two חצאי
זיתים. chatzei zeisim. שני מינים, shnei minim, you do not bring a
genre, two genres, you do
not bring a קרבן if it's two חצאי זיתים. chatzei zeisim. So
ממין אחד חייב, mimin echad chayav, the גמרא Gemara says פשיטא, pishita,
of course you're חייב chayav if it's two two half כזיתים, kezaysim,
that's obvious. So גמרא Gemara said ריש לקיש משום בר טוטיני, Resh
Lakish mishum Bar Tutini, interesting name, כגון שאכלו בשני תמחויין. kegon she'achalo
b'shnei tamchuyin. Let's say those two half חלב cheilev you ate were
part of different types of dishes. One was a half חלב cheilev
of stew and the other was a half חלב cheilev of I
don't know roasted. Okay, so... Maybe is the fact that they were
prepared differently in different dishes, although it's the same prohibition, make it
separate things that don't combine or are they fundamentally the same prohibition
and they do combine? See from, you know, the kidneys versus חלב
chelev of the whatever it is? Not necessarily the same. Could, I
mean, it could be parallel, but not the same. מהו דתימא, mahu
d'teima, I might have thought now because there's a position out there
of אליבא דרבי יהושע דאמר תמחויים מחולקין. aliba d'Rabbi Yehoshua d'amar tamchuim
mechulakin. There's a position of רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua that says that
those fact that they're different dishes would divide them. What does רבי
יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua say? He says, let's say it's not two halves,
let's say it's a full כזית. kezayis. So you have a full
כזית kezayis of חלב chelev from a stew and a full כזית
kezayis of חלב chelev from, like I said, I don't know, roast.
So in that case, he would say you bring two קרבנות, korbanos,
not one. Although we said that normally we define it as one
big act, he said if they are prepared differently, that actually defines
them as separate acts. So he's willing to look at the way
they're prepared differently to separate them to make you bring multiple קרבנות.
korbanos. Would he also separate them to prevent you from combining two
halves and say you don't even have to bring one קרבן? So
מהו דתימא, mahu d'teima, I might have thought, כי אמר רבי יהושע,
ki amar Rabbi Yehoshua, when רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says that if
they're prepared differently they're separate, לא שנא לקולא ולא שנא לחומרא, lo
shena l'kula v'lo shena l'chumra, it doesn't matter if we're going to
be lenient or strict. So we'll both make you bring multiple קרבנות
korbanos if it's a כזית kezayis and a כזית, kezayis, and we
won't make you bring any קרבן if it's a half and a
half. קא משמע לן דחייב. ka mashma lan d'chayiv. So therefore it
says no, as long as it's all חלב, chelev, the two halves
combine, even if they're different dishes. אלמא לחומרא אמר. alma l'chumra amar.
When does he say different dishes matter? To make it be strict,
to make you say that's enough of a basis to bring two
קרבנות. korbanos. לקולא לא אמר. l'kula lo amar. He's not going to
get you off the hook based on this. At the end of
the day, you ate a full כזית kezayis of חלב chelev even
though half was roasted and half was stewed. Okay, לא אמר. lo
amar. So that's one version, that the משנה Mishnah. is telling you
that even according to him, different dishes would still combine. Some, however,
say it's going the exact opposite. איכא דאמרי ika d'amri על סיפא,
al seifa, that we're focusing on the end of the משנה. Mishnah,
It says משני מינים פטור. mishnei minim patur. If it's two separate,
if it's a half, two separate genres like כזית kezayis and דם,
dam, of like חלב chelev and דם, dam, they don't combine. So
on that the גמרא Gemara. said פשיטא, pishita, isn't that obvious? That
they're separate sins, they don't combine. So אמר ריש לקיש משום בר
תותני, amar Resh Lakish mishum bar Tutni, כגון שאכלו בשני תמחויים. kegon
she'achlo bishnei tamchuim. No, it doesn't really, when it says it doesn't
combine, so here it's the opposite of what we said, it doesn't
combine, it doesn't really mean חלב chelev and דם. dam. When it
says two different things don't combine, it even means a חלב chelev
from a stew and a חלב chelev from a roast. Okay, that
two halves do not combine according to רבי יהושע. Rabbi Yehoshua. ואליבא
דרבי יהושע דאמר תמחויים מחולקין. v'aliba d'Rabbi Yehoshua d'amar tamchuim mechulakin. According
to רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua that says different dishes are separate to
bring multiple קרבנות. korbanos. דמהו דתימא כי אמר רבי יהושע לחומרא אמר
לקולא לא אמר. d'mahu d'teima ki amar Rabbi Yehoshua l'chumra amar l'kula
lo amar. I might have said he only says it to be
strict, to bring multiple קרבנות, korbanos, he wouldn't get you off the
hook if it's a half and a half. משום דאכלה בבי מיני,
mishum d'achla b'bei minei, לקולא לא אמר קא משמע לן. l'kula lo
amar ka mashma lan. So therefore it's telling you no, מבי מיני
פטור. mibei minei patur. מאי בי מיני? mai bei minei? What does
it mean two separate things, two genres you're פטור? patur? ממין אחד
הוא. mimin echad hu. It really means two types of חלב. chelev.
ואמאי קרי ליה בי מיני? v'amai kari lei bei minei? Why is
it calling it two? משום דאכלה בבי תמחויים. mishum d'achla b'bei tamchuim.
Because you're eating them, they were created in different pots, meaning they're
different types of dishes. וקתני פטור v'katani patur and he's saying you're
exempt. Any way in which it's two separate, even if it's חלב
chelev and חלב chelev but it's done differently, they're considered separate and
they don't combine. This is two different versions, right? No, not necessarily
by me and by you. What? No. אלמא לא שנא לקולא ולא
שנא לחומרא. alma lo shena l'kula v'lo shena l'chumra. It doesn't matter
whether to be lenient or strict, קאמר רבי יהושע. ka'amar Rabbi Yehoshua.
רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua is saying that they don't combine. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara has a question within רבי יהושע. Rabbi Yehoshua.
רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says that different pots means different קרבנות. korbanos.
If it's a כזית kezayis of חלב chelev stew and one roast,
it's two קרבנות. korbanos. Right before we just said that it's all
חלב, chelev, it's all one קרבן. He says the fact that they're
different like that means multiple. And the question is, would he go
so far to even be lenient based on that model? A half
and a half don't combine and there are two ways of reading
the משנה, Mishnah. whether he would be saying that in that case
it does combine or it doesn't combine. Would he be lenient to
get you off the hook? Okay, now the גמרא says like this,
מאי בי מיני? mai bei minei? I just did that. Okay. אלמא
לא שנא לקולא ולא שנא לחומרא. alma lo shena l'kula v'lo shena
l'chumra. מדסיפא מין אחד ובשני תמחויים. mide'seifa min echad u'bishnei tamchuim. Now
from the fact that the end we are saying is two types
of חלב, chelev, is חלב chelev just prepared two different ways and
we're saying it doesn't combine. רישא מין אחד ותמחוי אחד. reisha min
echad v'tamchui echad. So when the beginning it says that it does
combine, it doesn't only mean that it's חלב, chelev, it means it's
חלב chelev and the same dish. So now we're back to a
question, פשיטא, pishita, isn't that obvious? If the end means different dishes
don't combine, then the beginning when it says it does combine means
the same dish. So of course it combines. What, you know, that's
obvious. אמר רבינא, amar Ravina, כגון שהיתה לו ידיעה בינתיים. kegon she'haysa
lo yediya beintayim. No, here's another interesting question about two halves. What
if you became aware in the middle? Now we just said before,
if I had a כזית kezayis of חלב, chelev, became aware and
forgot and another כזית, kezayis, it splits it up into two acts
to bring two קרבנות. korbanos. Would I also say it splits it
up into two acts so that two חצי כזיתים chatzi kezaysim don't
combine? Right? It's the same type of a question about the two
dishes. It's one thing to say, you know, that certain things make
it multiple קרבנות, korbanos, but... Would it also go so far to
prevent you even from being one קרבן and saying it doesn't combine?
Okay? ואליבא דרבן גמליאל דאמר אין ידיעה לחצי שיעור. v'aliba d'Rabban Gamliel
d'amar ein yediya l'chatzi shiur. And this is going according to Rabban
Gamliel who actually says this, that becoming aware before you've actually finished
the amount for the sin, when you've only done half of the
amount, does not is not considered meaningful. It's not. You're still, yes,
it does not break up the act and you'd be חייב chayav
in the end. It's not. הכותב שתי אותיות בשתי העלמות. hakoseiv shtei
osiyos b'shtei helamos. Right? On שבת Shabbos you're only חייב chayav if
you write two letters. So let's say you wrote one letter and
then you remembered it was שבת, Shabbos, then you forgot again and
wrote another letter. אחד שחרית ואחד ערבית. echad shacharis v'echad arvis. One
in the morning and one in the evening, it was two states
of different states of awareness of being unaware. רבן גמליאל מחייב, Rabban
Gamliel mechayev, he says you're חייב, chayav, וחכמים פוטרין, v'Chachamim potrin, the
חכמים Chachamim exempt, the חכמים Chachamim say you became aware in the
middle, it completely divides the act. רבן גמליאל סבר אין ידיעה לחצי
שיעור, Rabban Gamliel savar ein yediya l'chatzi shiur, the fact that you
became aware after having done a half act is not really becoming
aware because you're not yet aware that you've sinned. You're only aware,
I mean that's another way of saying it. One way of saying
it is חומרא chumra versus קולא. kula. Another way of saying it
is, right, like we said before. Another way of saying it is
you're not really aware of having done a sin, you've only written
a half, so it's not called being aware. Okay? ורבנן סברי יש
ידיעה לחצי שיעור. v'Rabbanan savri yeish yediya l'chatzi shiur. No, being aware
divides it into two acts. So here we have two different types
of scenarios that you can divide something into two. According to רבי
יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua based on different dishes, according to the חכמים Chachamim
becoming aware, and everybody agrees that the aware case makes multiple acts
for multiple קרבנות, korbanos, and the question is would these things also
be effective for dividing up two half כזיתים kazeisim to say you
haven't even done one act and you don't have to bring a
קרבן. We have one minute. Let's read the משנה. Mishnah. Okay? כמה
ישהא באוכלין. kama yishei b'ochlin. How now here that we're talking about
eating two half כזיתים, kazeisim, we get into a very important principle
that applies to יום כיפור Yom Kippur and to מצה matzah which
is coming up, which is if you do an act over a
process because that's like eating two half כזיתים, kazeisim, when is it
defined as one act? One act of eating מצה, matzah, one act
of eating on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. How much of a break
between it would define it as different acts? כמה ישהא באוכלין. kama
yishei b'ochlin. So באוכלין b'ochlin when it comes to food, כאילו אוכל
קליות, k'ilu ochel kalyos, like you're eating like a nut, not nuts.
What what do they eat? What do the Israelis eat? What's that?
Like חמניות? chamaniyos? Sunflower seeds. Right, whatever, you know, but it's like
a little, a little, a little, meaning yes, it could be as
long you have to eat it, the גמרא will explain whether he's
being lenient or strict, but it means, you know, eating a little
bit but eating constant. That's how רבי מאיר looks at it, or
we'll explain that when we get to the גמרא. וחכמים אומרים v'Chachamim
omrim and the חכמים Chachamim say what we are normally used to,
עד שישהא מתחילה ועד סוף כדי אכילת פרס. ad sheyishei mitechila v'ad
sof k'dei achilas pras. You have to do it from the beginning
to the end the time it takes to eat half loaf of
bread. How much is half a loaf of bread? There's a debate
between רש"י Rashi and the רמב"ם. Rambam. רש"י Rashi says it is
eight כזיתים kazeisim and the רמב"ם Rambam says it's nine כזיתים. kazeisim.
So you're eating one כזית kazayis in the amount of time it
would normally take somebody to eat eight or nine כזיתים. kazeisim. So
it gives you like a lot of time, right? You don't have
to gobble it down. It's the amount of time it would normally
take to eat a quantity eight or nine times that much. How
long is that? Now, I don't know, there's debate, four minutes, nine
minutes, we'd normally מחמיר machmir based on, you know, it's like four
minutes is is a number that's thrown around. Now, I want to
say a very important question in interpreting this phrase. From the beginning
to the end of what? What do you think it means from
beginning to end? When you start to eat to when you finish?
From when you start to when you finish eating, that's certainly what
it sounds like. That's certainly רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom says it explicitly.
תוספות, Tosafos, if you look at תוספות, Tosafos, מתחילה ועד סוף כדי
אכילת פרס, mitechila v'ad sof k'dei achilas pras, מהכא מחמיר דתרי גווני
מאי שיעור פרס, חדא מן הפסקה שאם הפסיק בין אכילה לאכילה כשיעור
פרס. meihacha machmir d'trei gavni mai shiur pras, chada min hafsaqa she'im
hifsik bein achila l'achila k'shiur pras. How big is the break? Not
how big is it from the beginning to the end. There's a
huge difference to that question, right? Huge difference. Is are you measuring
the break or are you measuring the beginning of eating to the
end of eating? Right? And תוספות Tosafos reads it that way, but
the simple sense is certainly beginning of eating to the end of
eating. Okay, let's just finish the משנה. Mishna אכל אוכלין טמאין ושתה
משקין טמאין. achal ochlin t'meiin v'shasa mashkin t'meiin. Let's say you ate
טמא food. The הלכה halacha is that if you eat טמא food,
then you yourself become טמא. או שתה רביעית יין o shasa revi'is
yayin or another way, it's not about the act itself being a
sin but it's leading up to something, you drank a רביעית revi'is
of wine and then you're considered drunk and you're not allowed to
enter the בית המקדש. ונכנס למקדש ושהה כדי אכילת פרס. v'nichnas l'mikdash
v'shaha k'dei achilas pras. So if in the process of eating this
non- this טמא food or this wine, you if it took the
time of eating a פרס, pras, חייב. chayav. Then you're considered drunk
when you ate in the- ate when you entered the מקדש, Mikdash,
then you're considered טמא. רבי אליעזר אומר אם הפסיק בה או שנתן
בה מים כל שהוא פטור. Rabbi Eliezer omer im hifsik bah o
she'nasan bah mayim kol shehu patur. This is not really about general
things, it's just about being drunk. Since by the רביעית revi'is of
wine it's about being drunk, if you took any break when you
were drinking the wine or you added a little water, then we're
not going to call you drunk just because you drank a רביעית
revi'is of wine. So that's a different issue of defining you as
drunk for going to the בית המקדש, but the prime issue is
over how much space you define it as one act of eating,
huge implications להלכה. l'halacha. We will continue after שבת. Shabbos. Good שבת
Shabbos to everyone. We are on דף כ"ד. Daf Chaf Daled. We're
starting from the bottom of דף כ"ג עמוד ב'. Daf Chaf Gimmel
Amud Bais. The משנה says: המאכיל מן הבהמה עד שלא תצא נפשה.
Hamachil min habehema ad shelo taitzei nafsha. If someone feeds another from
an animal before its soul has departed, even though he slaughtered it,
he is עובר over on a לאו. lav. And he is not
עובר over on the איסור issur of אבר מן החי. ever min
hachai. And if he slaughtered it, even though it's still מפרכסת, mefarkeses,
it's not אבר מן החי. ever min hachai. The גמרא says: מנא
הני מילי? Mena hani mili? What is the source for this? It
says in the תורה, Torah, לא תאכלו על הדם. Lo sochlu al
hadam. You shall not eat over the blood. This means you shouldn't
eat the meat while the blood is still in it, meaning before
it's fully dead.